Guide to the Roberts, Ursula, Incoming correspondence, ca. 1910-1960
Department of Special Collections
Ursula Roberts, Incoming correspondence,
ca. 1910-1960
M0908
Roberts Ursula
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
British poet, writer and political activist. During the Edwardian period, while in her 20s, wife of a pacifist Socialist clergyman, Roberts first took an active part in the campaign for women's suffrage. Using her pseudonym Susan Miles for most of her writer's career, she published her first inflammatory pamphlet THE CAUSE OF PURITY AND WOMEN'S SUFFRAGE in 1912. By the end of the first World War, the date of the earliest letters in this archive, her interest had expanded to such feminist issues as the admission of women to the clergy. But it was in the 1920s and 1930s while part of the literary circle which revolved around ADELPHI MAGAZINE, launched by Katherine Mansfield's widower and D.H. Lawrence's closest friend J. Middleton Murry, that she became an active participant in the anti-war movement which swept British left-wing intellectual circles, until it became clear to many of her friends that "peace at any price" meant surrender to Nazi and Fascist dictatorship. (quoted from dealer's description)
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1997.
Provenance
Purchased, 1997.
Biography
The British writer Ursula (Wyllie) Roberts was born in 1887, the daughter of the "ardent conservative" Lt.-Col. R.J.H. Wyllie. By early adulthood she had rejected many of the beliefs of her upbringing and become an "idealistic agnostic" and pacifist. She married the socialist, pacifist Reverend William Corbett Roberts in 1909 and began her career as a poet, novelist and activist, publishing "The Cause of Purity and Women's Suffrage"-"a tough-minded pamphlet on prostitution which confronts low wages and child abuse"-in 1912. For later publications Ursula Roberts used the pseudonym "Susan Miles." The poems and stories of "Miss Miles" were published in various journals and volumes. Her major books are Dunch (1918), a book of free verse sketches about Crick, "an old-style rural parish" in Northants, Blind Men Crossing a Bridge (1934), Rabboni (1942), a memoir of her late husband in 1955, and the verse novel Lettice Delmer (1958). Roberts was active in peace and women's movements throughout her career, maintaining her pacifist ideals even into the Cold War when many British intellectuals had abandoned theirs. In the 1960s, she became a strong supporter of nuclear disarmament.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
This collection, consisting almost entirely of incoming letters to Ursula Roberts, spans half a century, from the 1910s to the 1960s. It includes correspondence discussing the work of "Susan Miles" and that of friends and literary associates. Also included are numerous letters from members of the Peace Pledge Union (a major pacifist organization), from other peace activists (some of them prominent religious figures), and from various women's activists. Suffrage and the ordination of women are key issues. Letters are filed alphabetically by last name (except when unavailable) of correspondent. Major correspondents include: Phoebe Hesketh, Yvonne Lubbock, Sylvia O'Malley, Dorothy Plowman, Max Plowman, Canon Guy Rogers, Maude Royden, Gordon Scott, Reverend A. P. Shephard, Dick Shepperd, Susan Stebbing, and Paula Wikins. The number of letters from each correspondent is noted in parentheses in the listing. Many of the letters have been annotated by Roberts, often many years later, explaining the context or significance of the contents.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Alexander, Samuel.; Barlow, Anna.; Blackburn, Thomas.; Bodkin, Maud.; Boulton, Walter.; Brailsford, H.H.; Brasch, Charles.; Browne, Nancy.; Cestr, Gerald.; Chase, Lewis.; Cockin, Arthur Smith.; Collins, L. John, (Lewis John); Collins, Vera H.; Courtney, Kathleen, Dame, 1878-1974.; Cram, J.M.C.; Dalton,Hugh.; Day, Mabel.; De la Mare, Walter, 1873-1956.; Dearmer, Percy.; Dickinson, Patric.; Driberg, Tom, 1905-1976.; Ebor, William.; Edyell, Beatrice.; Fawcett, Philippa.; Fay, Judith.; Fraser, Vera.; Fry, Ruth.; Hamilton King, H.E.; Heppenstall, Rayner.; Hesketh, Phoebe.; Holbrook, David.; Housman, Lawrence.; Hughes, Molly.; Hyett, V.A.; Isaacs, Susan.; Joad, C.E.M.; Kershaw, John.; Kingsley, Martin.; Levett, Elizabeth.; Lewis, Naomi.; Lubock, Yvonne.; Markreiter, C.G.; McBride, Mary F.; Micklem, Nathaniel.; Moore, Sturge.; O'Malley, I.B. (Ida Beatrice), 1873-; Oakley, Hilda D.; Oberholzen, Enid.; Palmer, Bernard.; Pankhurst, E. Sylvia, (Estelle Sylvia), 1882-1960.; Plowman, Dorothy.; Plowman, Max, 1883-1941.; Raven, Charles E.; Reuss, Rose.; Ridley, Simon.; Rogers, T. Guy, Canon.; Royden, A. Maude.; Sangster, Paul.; Sangster, William E.; Savage, Derek.; Scott, Gordon.; Seaman, Owen, Sir.; Haile-Selassie, Teferra.; Shepherd, Arthur P., Archdeacon of Dudley.; Sheppard, Dick.; Stebbing, Susan.; Wells, Carlton F.; Wickham, Anna.; Wikins, Paula.; British literature--20th century.; Peace movements.; Women--Suffrage.
Collection Contents
- Alexander, Prof. Samuel 1935, n.d., (2 letters) (Folder 1)
- Allen, Mrs. Roland n.d., (1 letter) (Folder 1)
  Annotated by Roberts.
- Anson, Peter F. 1967, (1) (Folder 1)
- Ashley, Corbette (1), 1935 (Folder 1)
- Asquith, Anthony 1958, (1) (Folder 1)
- Attlee, M.A.S. 1935, (1) (Folder 1)
- Barlow, Lady Anna 1938, n.d., (2) (Folder 1)
- Baxter, K. 1961., (1) (Folder 1)
- Beaumont, Geoffrey 1947, (1) (Folder 1)
- Blackburn, Thomas poem "In the Fire." 1954, n.d., (2) (Folder 1)
- Blomfield, Frances Cuttwell 1956, (1) (Folder 1)
- Bodkin, Maud 1941, n.d., (3) (Folder 2)
- Booth, Alan R. 1962, (1) (Folder 3)
- Boulton, Rev. Walter n.d., (2) (Folder 3)
- Brailsford, H.N., ed. The New Leader1924, 1936, (2) (Folder 3)
- Brasch, Charles, Landfall New Zealand Quarterly 1958-1959, (2) (Folder 3)
- Browne, Nancy 1938, n.d., (4) (Folder 3)
  Re: Dick Sheppard
- Burnet, I. Compton (?) (Folder 3)
  (1 copy of letter from Roberts to I.C.B.)
- Byrde, N.B., (1 letter) (Folder 3)
  addressed to Mr. Roberts, n.d.
- Castemar, William 1943, (1) (Folder 3)
- Cecil (?) 1935, (1) (Folder 3)
- Cestr, Gerald, Bishop of Chester 1967, (2) (Folder 3)
- Chamberlain, Rev. Elsie 1960, (1) (Folder 4)
- Chapman, R.W., The Clarendon Prefs 1922, (1) (Folder 4)
- Chase, Lewis, Peking University 1922., (1) (Folder 4)
  Re: His article on her work, teaching English, R. Ellis Roberts, the Chinese Renaissance.
- Christopher (Wansey?) 1962, (1) (Folder 4)
- Cockin, Arthur Smith (?) Bishop of Bristol, Dublin University (1) n.d. (Folder 4)
- Collins, Canon L. John 1962, 1966., (2) (Folder 4)
  Re: Disarmament, Dick Sheppard
- Collins, Vere H. 1950., (2) (Folder 5)
  Poem by V.H.C.?
- Courtney, Miss K.D. 1935., (2) (Folder 6)
  Re: Peace, Suffrage Movement, politics, the L.N.V.
- Cowley, P. (Reverend Patrick Cowley?) 1935, (1) (Folder 6)
- Cram, J.M.C. 1953., (1) (Folder 6)
- Dalton, Hugh 1937., (1) (Folder 6)
- Day, Mabel 1918, 1937., (2) (Folder 6)
- de Burgh, W.F. 1935, (1) (Folder 6)
- de? (de la Mare?), W.F. 1929, (1) (Folder 6)
- de la Mare, Walter 1922, (1) (Folder 6)
- Dearmer, Percy 1913-1914., (2) (Folder 6)
- Dickinson, Patric n.d., (1) (Folder 6)
  Forwarded, with unsigned note by Roberts?
- Dougall (?), L. 1916., (1) (Folder 6)
- Driberg, Tom, M.P. 1962, (1) (Folder 6)
- Earl, Ethel n.d., (1) (Folder 7)
- Earnsworth, Mary C. SMV 1956, (1) (Folder 7)
- Ebor, William 1939-1940, (3) (Folder 7)
  one addressed to "Mr. Bird." Annotated by Roberts.
- Edyell, Prof. Beatrice 1923., (1) (Folder 7)
- Ethel (?) 1922-1929, n.d., (4) (Folder 8)
- Fanks (?), Alfred (?) n.d., (1) (Folder 9)
- Fawcett, Philippa 1936, n.d., (2) (Folder 9)
  Re: Refugees, L.N.V., G. Lansbury's funeral.
- Fay, Judith 1934, n.d., (6) (Folder 10)
- Fer (?), Elisavita (?) 1961, (1) (Folder 11)
- Fraser, (?) 1926., (1) (Folder 11)
- Fraser, Vera n.d., (1) (Folder 11)
- Fry, Ruth 1935-1936, (2) (Folder 11)
- Gardner, Brian 1965, (1) (Folder 11)
- Godber, Joseph, M.P. 1961, (1) (Folder 11)
- Goodyear, R.E. 1935., (1) (Folder 11)
- Gould, Barbara Ayrton 1935, (1) (Folder 11)
- Gray, Reverend A. Herbert n.d., (1) (Folder 11)
- Grensted, L.W. 1935, (1) (Folder 11)
- Hamilton King, H.E. 1918., (1) (Folder 11)
  Author of "The Disciples." Annotated by Roberts.
- Harton, Sybil n.d., (1) (Folder 11)
- Hebert, A. Gabriel n.d., (1) (Folder 11)
- Heppenstall, Rayner 1937-1957., (4) (Folder 12)
  Re: "Blind Men Crossing a Bridge" in Adelphi, Heppenstall's poems, Eric Gill, Max Plowman, P.P.U., Basque children, Murry, organized pacifism, B.B.C., nuclear bombs, smoking, English hypocrisy.
- Hesketh, Phoebe 1961-1972., (8) (Folder 13)
  Re: Susan Miles' poetry and "near-blindness," Day Lewis, Herbert Palmer's death, H.P. Villon.
- Heywood (?), Rosalin 1969, (1) (Folder 14)
- Holbrook, David 1965-1966, (3) (Folder 14)
- Housman, Lawrence 1922-1923, (2) (Folder 15)
- Hugel, F. V. 1919, (1) (Folder 15)
  addressed to "Dear Reverend Sir"
- Hughes, Molly 1942, (2) (Folder 15)
- Hyett, V.A. 1934, n.d., (2) (Folder 15)
- Isaacs, Susan 1935, (1) (Folder 16)
- Joad, C.E.M. 1935, (2) (Folder 16)
  (in secretary's hand and signature) and 1938. Re: "Pax," Susan Stebbing. Annotated by Roberts.
- Kershaw, John 1955., (2) (Folder 16)
  Including Re: Anna Wickham.
- Laski, Margharita 1971, (1) (Folder 16)
- Lea, F.A. 1957, (1) (Folder 16)
- Levett, Elizabeth, King's College n.d., (2) (Folder 16)
- Levett, ? (possibly Elizabeth) 1929., (1) (Folder 16)
- Lewis, Naomi 1956, 1972, (4) (Folder 17)
- Liverpool, Clifford 1964, (1) (Folder 17)
- Lubock, Yvonne 1961-1966, (7) (Folder 18)
- Margaret (?) 1958, (1) (Folder 19)
- Markreiter, C.G., letter to 1959, (1) (Folder 19)
  poem by (1) (translation of "Dies Irae").
- Kingsley, Martin, letter to 1968, 1) (Folder 19)
- Matthews, Rev. Charles H.S. 1934, (1) (Folder 19)
- Maurice Brown Ltd. 1931., (1) (Folder 19)
  Re: "Miss Tabernacle"
- Maychurch (?) 1918, (1) (Folder 19)
- McBride, Mary F. n.d., (1) (Folder 19)
- Meigher (?), Moira (?) 1924, (1) (Folder 19)
- Micklem, Nathaniel 1957-1958, (2) (Folder 19)
- Moore, Sturge, daughter of 1954., (1) (Folder 19)
  Letter requesting reminiscences of her father for a book. Annotated by Roberts.
- Morris, Stuart 1937., (1) (Folder 19)
  P.P.U.
- Morrison, Sybil 1962., (1) (Folder 19)
- Muir, Willa 1968, (1) (Folder 19)
- O'Malley, Ida 1918-1937., (6) (Folder 20)
  Re: "The Common Cause" Suffrage Movement, Dr. Royden, Church League, sanctions, "The late War and Mussolini," Malta military, non-resistance, Ethiopia, O'Malley's "Florence Nightengale," the P.P.U.
- Oakley, Hilda D. 1936. Annotated by Roberts., (1) (Folder 21)
- Oberholzen, Enid 1969-1970, (2) (Folder 21)
- Orld (?), Herman 1943-1948, (3) (Folder 21)
- Palmer, Bernard, ed. Church Times, copy of letter (1) to the editor by Roberts, (1) letter 1970-1971. (Folder 22)
- Pankhurst, Sylvia New Times and Ethiopia News,1938., (1) (Folder 22)
  re: sanctions and war, Italy, dictators, appeasement, imperialists, pacifism. Annotated by Roberts.
- Philpotts, Adelaide 1926-1937., (4) (Folder 23)
- Plowman, Dorothy n.d., (10) (Folder 24)
  Re: Max Plowman, poetry, J.M.M., refugees, religion, Peace News, P.P.U., death of Max Plowman, Basque children.
- Plowman, Max 1937-1938., (6) (Folder 25)
  Re: P.P.U., Dick Sheppard.
- Ponsonby, ? 1935., (1) (Folder 26)
  Re: "PAX"
- Porter, Alan 1922, (1) (Folder 26)
- Pritchard, V. 1968, (1) (Folder 26)
- Raven, Charles E. n.d., (3) (Folder 27)
- Reeves, James 1959, (1) (Folder 28)
- Reid, H.M. (Folder 28)
- Reuss, Rose 1940., (1) (Folder 28)
  Wife of Austrian sculptor, refugee. Annotated by Roberts.
- Reynolds, Reginald n.d., (1) (Folder 29)
- Ridley, Simon 1966., (1) (Folder 29)
- Rien, E.V., Penguin Classics 1954., (2) (Folder 29)
  Re: Susan Stebbing, the Gospel story.
- Rogers, Canon T. Guy 1949-1967, n.d., (11) (Folder 30)
- Rose, Walter 1938, (1) (Folder 31)
- Royden, A. Maude 1918-1953., (9) (Folder 32)
  Re: Religion, women's ordination, Roberts' work.
- Sangster, Paul 1963-1965., (3) (Folder 33)
- Sangster, William E. 1959-1960, (2) (Folder 33)
- Savage, Derek 1968, (3) (Folder 34)
- Scott, Dr. Gordon, "A Country Doctor" 1961-1965., (5) (Folder 35)
  Re: Facing Retirement.
- Scripture, E.W. 1927., (1) (Folder 36)
- Seaman, Sir Owen 1923, (2) (Folder 36)
- Selassie, Haile (secretary of, Dr. Bayen) 1936., (1) (Folder 36)
  Re: "his every effort for justice."
- Shepherd, Arthur P., Archdeacon of Dudley 1941-1965, (7) (Folder 37)
- Sheppard, Dick 1937., (7) (Folder 38)
  Includes newspaper clipping.
- Sheppard, Edgar 1937., (1) (Folder 38)
  Re: Dick Sheppard, biographical details.
- Smith (?) 1918?-1923, (2) (Folder 39)
- Soskice, Julia n.d., (1) (Folder 39)
- Stebbing, Susan 1922-1938, (4) (Folder 40)
  Re: poetry, fascist Chamberlain, Benes, Hitler, France, Mein Kampf, Marx, Trotsky, Lenin. Annotated by Roberts, including the note: "I had masses of letters from [Susan Stebbing], but I have destroyed them. She would have hated them to have been read or her biography to have been written."
- St. Albans, Philip (?) 1947, (1) (Folder 41)
- Swann, Donald "A fellow A.P.F. member," 1963., (1) (Folder 41)
  re: setting Roberts' verse to music, Michael Flanders.
- Tasker, Robert I. 1936., (1) (Folder 41)
  Re: editorial on Germany.
- Thomas, Alice Lloyd 1934., (1) (Folder 41)
- Tibble, Anne 1935, (1) (Folder 41)
- Waddell, Helen (Folder 41)
- Weatherhead, Rev. Dr. Leslie D. 1968, (1) (Folder 41)
- Wells, Carlton F. 1965-1966, (3) (Folder 42)
- Whitehead, A.N. 1924., (1) (Folder 42)
  Re: Susan Stebbing. Annotated by Roberts.
- Wickham, Anna One to "Young Andrew." n.d., (2) (Folder 43)
  Includes poems by Wickham. Annotated by Roberts.
- Wikins, Paula Writer 1934-1940, (9) (Folder 44)
  Wife of Indian communist writer
- Williams, Edith M. 1964, (1) (Folder 45)
- Wisdom, John 1970, (1) (Folder 45)
- Woodhouse, Charles 1961., (1) (Folder 45)
  Addressed to "Mr. Palmer."
- Wragg, Arthur n.d., (2) (Folder 45)
  Re: Dick Sheppard's book, illustration, P.P.U.
- Young, Wayland 1962, (1) (Folder 45)
- unidentified/signature illegible (Folder 46)